A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Office of Reports, Photograph Exhibit Files FA1153
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Office of Reports, Photograph Exhibit Files
1961-1987
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1153
4.53 Cubic Feet 8 Hollinger boxes and 4 oversize document boxes
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
When requesting to view audiovisual material, please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1916). Researchers are asked to check the "Restrictions" note for each Title. If a Title does not currently have an access copy, please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas. During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
This material was transferred to the RAC in 2019 and was ingested by the RAC as Accession 2019:066.
Scope and Contents
Collection contains records that the Ford Foundation Office of Reports created to plan and document various photograph exhibit projects. Exhibits were produced to promote the work of the Ford Foundation in broad program areas such as support for American theater and women in developing countries as well as the work of individual initiatives and artists.
Photographs, photograph negatives, slides, exhibit panel proofs, and arrangement maps document how the Office of Reports planned the images, text, and configuration of exhibits. In addition to containing images that were selected and under consideration for use in exhibits, the collection also includes photographs that were taken of exhibits. Correspondence, memos, drafts, notes, purchase orders, invoices, and expense reports document the planning, production, and financing of exhibits. Much of the correspondence was created by Graphics Manager Nancy Boggs and her fellow Office of Reports staff member Ruth Neumann. The records they produced show how the Office of Reports reached out to Ford Foundation staff and external organizations for photographs to use in exhibits, contracted consultants for photography, exhibit design, exhibit production, and exhibit installation, and arranged and promoted exhibit events.
Other materials in the collection such as brochures, newspaper clippings, newsletters, and publications generally provide background information on the subjects of the different exhibits. The exhibit producers may have used these resources as reference materials when planning the exhibits.
Arrangement
Collection consists of one series.
Original order was maintained as much as possible.
Collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Photograph exhibit files, 1961-1987
Ford Foundation; Exhibitions; Exhibitions -- Design; Photographs
- Photograph exhibit files, 1961-1987; 1; 4.53 Cubic Feet About 7 LGL size Hollinger boxes, 1 half-LGL size Hollinger box, and 4 oversize document boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series consists of the files that the Ford Foundation Office of Reports created to plan and document various exhibit projects. Records suggest that Graphics Manager Nancy Boggs and her fellow Office of Reports staff member Ruth Neumann were responsible for much of the planning and execution of these projects. Their correspondence shows how they reached out to Ford Foundation staff and external organizations for photographs to use in exhibits, how they contracted consultants for photography, exhibit design, exhibit production, and exhibit installation, and how they arranged and promoted exhibit events. Exhibits were produced to promote the work of the Ford Foundation in broad program areas such as support for American theater and women in developing countries as well as the work of individual initiatives and artists.
  The series contains photographs, photograph negatives, and slides that were selected and under consideration for use in the different exhibits. There are also drafts of exhibit panel proofs that document what text the exhibit producers wanted to include as well as arrangement plans and maps that document how the exhibit producers wanted to configure the display materials. Purchase orders, invoices, and expense reports provide additional information on the planning and production of exhibits. Other materials such as brochures, newspaper clippings, newsletters, and publications generally provide background information on the subjects of the different exhibits. The exhibit producers may have used these resources as reference materials when planning the exhibits. A file in the series that regards the Mississippi Action for Community Education (MACE) and Delta Foundation also includes audio recordings of interviews with different people involved with the organizations.
  Lastly, there are still images within the series that provide evidence of the actual exhibits. They are photographs of the finished exhibit panels and display spaces.
  - Mexico City exhibit - Modern Educational Aids, circa 1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Still images are photographs of panels at Modern Educational Aids exhibit.
  - Population exhibit, 1970; File contains still images. Sill images include both photographs and photographs negatives. (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
    Still images in the file include:
    Group of photographs sent to Nancy Boggs from Professor Egon Diczfalusy at the Swedish Medical Research Council Reproductive Endocrinology Research Unit in 1970. Photographs are numbered, and there is an index describing them. Not all of the photographs described in the index are contained within the file.
    These images are related to the other photographs and photograph negatives in the file that were used for the Ford Foundation's Population exhibit about fertility control research. Several of these images are photomicrographs showing salt "ferns" in women's saliva at different stages of ovulation. A few of the exhibit photographs have captions on their backs that include information about the photographer and what the image depicts.
  - Latin America: The Process of Development exhibit, 1983-1984; File contains realia. Items include pieces of an exhibit display panel. (Box 9, Folder 5-8)
  - Labor of Love: The Training of a Fine Arts Curator exhibit, 1969; File contains still images. Images include photographs and a photo negative sheet. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Photographs in the file are of text panels for the Labor of Love: The Training of a Fine Arts Curator exhibit. Photo negative sheet shows selected images of exhibit.
  - Photograph assignments, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photograph exhibits, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Program Related Investments (PRI) exhibit, 1981-1983; File contains still images. Images include photographs, photograph negatives, a photo negative sheet, and slides. (Box 2, Folder 13-17)
    Photograph negatives, photo negative sheet, and slides are images of the Program Related Investments (PRI) exhibit. The photographs in the file were used in an exhibit at the Studio Museum in Harlem. The Studio Museum in Harlem was a PRI recipient featured in the PRI exhibit. These photographs have captions on their backs.
  - Population exhibit, circa 1969-1970; File contains still image. (Box 10, Folder 18)
    Image is a photograph used in the Population exhibit. Description on the back of the photograph reads "Basque, University of Chicago, Workshop on Family Planning, Summer 1969"
  - Program Related Investments (PRI) exhibit captions, 1974-1983 (Box 3, Folder 19-21)
  - North Carolina Fund exhibit, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Theater exhibit - On Stage!, 1978-1980; File contains still images. The images are photographs. (Box 3, Folder 23-25)
    Photographs in the file are of theater actors performing. Descriptions on the back of the photographs name the performers.
  - Workers on the Land: West/Southwest exhibit, 1981-1983; File contains still images. Images include photographs and photograph negatives. (Box 4, Folder 26-27)
    Photographs and photograph negatives used for promotion of the Workers on the Land: West/Southwest exhibit. Exhibit featured photographs taken by Bill Ravanesi.
  - Asian Treasures exhibit, 1983; File contains still images. Images include photograph negatives and slides. (Box 4, Folder 28-33)
    Photograph negatives are likely pictures used in the Asian Treasures exhibit. Slides are pictures of the exhibit.
  - The Many Splendid Culture of India exhibit, 1985; File contains still images. Images include photographs and photograph negatives of different sizes. File contains realia. Items include pieces of a collage display. (Box 5, Folder 34-37)
    Photographs and photograph negatives are pictures that were selected and under consideration for use in The Many Splendid Culture of India exhibit. Some photographs have brief captions describing where in the exhibit they were to be featured. There are also paper printouts of exhibit photographs that have captions describing the subject matter of the pictures.
  - Eakins Press Foundation exhibit - O, Write My Name, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Theater exhibit - On Stage!, circa 1980 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    Photographs in the file are of the On Stage! exhibit. Their backs are numbered.
  - Ford Foundation Women's Programs exhibit, 1984-1986; File contains still images. Images are photograph negatives of different sizes. (Box 5, Folder 40-42)
    Photograph negatives are pictures used for the Ford Foundation Women's Program exhibit.
  - Workers on the Land: West/Southwest exhibit, circa 1981; File contains still images. Images are photographs. (Box 11, Folder 43)
    Photographs in the file are of the text used in the Workers on the Land: West/Southwest exhibit.
  - Tamarind Lithography Workshop exhibit, 1969; Files contains still images. Images are photographs glued to cardstock. (Box 11, Folder 44)
    Photographs are of the Tamarind Lithography Workshop exhibit.
  - Mississippi Action for Community Education (MACE)/Delta Foundation exhibit, 1979; File contains still images. Images are photographs. (Box 6, Folder 45-49)
    There is a group of Polaroid photographs of the MACE/Delta Foundation exhibit. There are also photographs of the first mechanical cotton picker that the Mississippi Department of Archives and History sent to the Ford Foundation for use in the exhibit.
    - Mississippi Action for Community Education (MACE) - Parts 1 and 2, 1979 September 18; 1/4 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 15612)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
      Part 1, Side 1: Mound Bayou - Old man, old house
      YICPP supervisors and workers
      Mrs. Shaw, Mayor's assistant
      Mayor of Mount Bayou
      Part 2, Side 2:
      Bicycle wheel factory manager
      Mayor of Metcalfe
    - Mississippi Action for Community Education (MACE) - Parts 3 and 4, 1979 September 18; 1/4 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 15613)
      Part 3, Side 1:
      End Metcalfe Mayor
      Shirley?, Assistant to Mayor
      Supervisor of YCIPP
      Larry Farmer
      Finance Officer
      Orestes Carmicle
      Part 4, Side 2:
      Delta Foundation staff
      Finance person?
      Anti-Crime Director
      Henry Mills, Delta Foundation Public Relations
      Ben Marshall, Finance Officer, Delta Foundation
      Finance Assistant, Delta Foundation
      Secretary, Delta Foundation
    - Mississippi Action for Community Education (MACE) - Part 5, 1979 September 18; 1/4 inch audio cassette (Box 1, Tape AV 15614)
      Part 5, Side 1
      Director of Training, Delta Foundation and Malcolm Walls
      Side 2 is blank.
  - Theater Reawakening exhibit, 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 50-51)
  - Women in Least Developed Countries exhibit, 1977-1980; File contains still images. Images include slides, photographs, photo negative sheets, and a photograph negative. (Box 6, Folder 52-55)
    Slides, photographs, and photo negative sheets are pictures that were selected and under consideration for use in the Women in Least Developed Countries exhibit. The photograph negative is an image of text used in the exhibit.
  - Latin America: The Process of Development exhibit, 1984-1987; File contains still images. Images include photographs, photograph negatives, and slides. (Box 7, Folder 56-60)
    There are photographs and photograph negatives that are pictures of the Latin America: The Process of Development exhibit. There are also photographs, photograph negatives, and slides that are images that were used in the exhibit.
  - Program Related Investments (PRI) exhibit, 1982-1983 (Box 7, Folder 61-62)
  - Women in Least Developed Countries exhibit, 1975-1980 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Women in Least Developed Countries exhibit - Correspondence, 1976-1980; File includes still images. Images are photographs glued to a piece of cardstock. File includes realia. Item is a piece of tie-dyed material glued to the same cardstock as the images. (Box 8, Folder 64-66, Box 12, Folder 67)
    Photographs in the file are related to the Small Industries Development Organization (SIDO) tie-dye and embroidery project in Tanzania. Some photographs show women in embroidered designs from Liberia. There is also a photograph of a class of graduates from the tie-dye and embroidery training program. The Ford Foundation Nairobi, Kenya Field Office sent photographs like these to the Office of Reports in New York for the Women in Least Developed Countries exhibit.
    There is also a sample of tie-dyed material made with fruits, herbs, and wax indigenous to East Africa.